Guide to the Victor Serge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1934-1947; Series I; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Gorkin, Julián, 1939-46 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Gorkin, 1940 Apr 6
      See also: Comision Socialista Internacional Mundo Partido Obrero de Unificaci'on Marxista Box 2, folder 96
    - Guérin, Daniel, 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Guzmán, Eulalia, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Hook, Sidney, 1943 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "I" general, 1942, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Intercontinentale du livre, 1947 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Kagan, George, 1941 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - "L" general, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Lam, Wilfredo, 1944 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 43a)
    - Largo Caballero, Francisco, 1940, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Laurat, Lucien, 1939-47 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Lepp, Ignace, 1940-41, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Levitas, S. M.
      See: The New Leader, Box 1, folder 61
    - "M" general, 1946-47, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Macdonald, Dwight, 1942-46, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
      See also: Box 2, folder 96; Box 4, folder 228
    - Macdonald, Nancy, 1940-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Magdaleno, Mauricio, 1941 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Malaquais, Jean, 1940-45, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Manheim, Ralph, 1946-47 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Martinet, Marcel, 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Marx, Magdeleine, 1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Modern Review (New York), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Mounier, Emmanuel, 1938-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
      See also: Box 21, folder 644
    - Mundo, 1944-45 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - The Nation (New York), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      See also: Box 2, folder 98
    - Németh, André, 1940 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - The New International (New York), 1938-39 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - The New Leader (New York), 1942-47 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Nin, Andrés, 1936 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 61a)
    - Now, 1946 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Partido Obrero de Unificaci'on Marxista, 1937-45 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Partisan Review (New York), 1942, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Paz, Magdeleine
      See: Magdeleine Marx, Box 1, folder 54
    - Paz, Octavio, 1944 Oct (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Pierre-Quint, Léon, 1940 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Pivert, Marceau, 1942-45 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      See also: Mundo, Box 1, folder 57
    - Plisnier, Charles, 1939, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Politics (New York), 1947 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Pommera, Marcelle
      See: Lucien Laurat, Box 1, folder 45
    - El popular, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Reynal & Hitchcock, [1946 Apr?] (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Roland Holst-Van der Schalk, Henriette, 1940 Apr 17 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Rosenthal, Gérard, 1939 Apr 26 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "S" general, 1938-47 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Shachtman, Max
      See: Box 12, folder 422
    - Soviet Union. Glavnoe upravlenie po delam literatury i izdatelstv, 1934, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Thomas, Fanny, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Thomas, Norman, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Time (New York), 1946-47 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Todo, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      See also: Box 12, folder 430
    - Trotskaia, Nataliia Ivanovna, 1942 Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1936, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      Includes: Trotsky's business card
    - Twice a Year (New York), 1947 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Ultimas noticias, 1944 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Valadés, José C., 1941-42 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Vauthier, R., 1939, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - La Voz israelita (Mexico), 1946 Sep 24 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Werth, Leon, 1939-41 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Workers Defense League, 1942 Mar 20 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Sent by Serge, Julián Gorkin,
      Marceau Pivert, and Gustave Regler
    - Wullens, Maurice, 1940-42, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Unidentified letters from Serge, 1940-46 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      Typescript carbon (some corrected)
    - Unidentified letters to Serge, 1939-47, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Kibalchich, Jeannine
      See: Box 2, folder 85
    - Kibalchich, Liouba Roussakova, 1936-47, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Kibalchich, Vlady, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Other family, 1945-47, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Gomez, Louise to Julian Gomez, 1942 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Macdonald, Dwight to Julián Gorkin, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Nachmann, Gustava to Günter Reimann, 1945 Sep 18 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Wolfe, Bertram David to The Nation, 1941 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 98)
- Writings, 1912-1947; Series II; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into nine subseries:
  Articles, Books, Conferences, Newspaper and Journal
  Clippings, Notes, Open Letters, Poems, Reviews, and
  Writings of Others. Each subseries is arranged
  alphabetically by title.
  - ARTICLES
    - "1er mai 44," typescript carbon, 1944 Apr 13 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - "A-t-on le droit de tuer ses adversaires politiques?," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - "Alger, point tournant de la guerre mondiale," typescript carbon, 1942 Nov 11 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - "Alice et Otto Ruhle sont morts...," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Jun 27 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - "L'alternative: démocratie russe!," typescript carbon, corrected, 1946 Mar (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - "Amenaza sobre el Caucaso," typescript, 1941 Oct 29 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - "L'anarchisme," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - "L'anniversaire du 15 janvier: Karl Liebknecht et Rosa Luxembourg"
      See: Box 21, folder 657
    - "L'appareil central du Komintern," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Feb (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - "Les armées invisibles," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - "L'assassinat de Léon Trotsky," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Mar (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - "L'assassinat de Trotsky (d'après les journaux américains du moment)" typescript, corrected, 1940 Aug (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - "Asuneo Andres Nin," typescript (Box 3, Folder 110)
      Includes: Notes, holograph and
      typescript
    - "Au seuil d'une révolution"
      See: Box 21, folder 651
    - "Autriche 1934," typescript, 1937 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - "L'avenir de l'URSS," typescript carbon, corrected, 1941 Dec (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - "L'avenir du socialisme," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - "Les aveux de Mratchkovski," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - "L'aviation dans la guerre des continents," typescript carbon, 1942 Jul (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - "L'axe a perdu la guerre d'Afrique," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Jan 7 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - "L'axe fléchit," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Jan 19 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - "Barcelone vue de Moscou," typescript, corrected, 1937 Mar 3 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - "Bas-fonds à Guadalajara," draft, typescript, corrected, 1945 Jun (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - "La bataille de Leningrad (souvenirs de 1919)," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 120)
      Includes: Spanish version, "Batallas
      por Leningrado," typescript carbon,
      corrected; clipping regarding
      article, [19]41 Sep 27
    - "La bataille des terres-noires...," typescript, corrected, 1942 Jul (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - "Bessarabie et Dobzoudja," typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - "La bête humaine," typescript, 1936 Sep 12 (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - "Bilan de la réaction stalinienne," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1941 Oct 18 (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - "Le bilan d'une année"
    - "Bilan provisoire de la campagne de Russie," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Feb 5 (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - "Le cadavre nu," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1946 Jan-Feb (Box 3, Folder 126)
    - "Les causes de l'impérialisme soviétique," typescript carbon, corrected (3 copies), 1947 Nov (Box 3, Folder 127)
      Includes: Spanish version, "Causas
      del imperialismo sovietico,"
      typescript carbon, corrected, and
      fragment of printed version
    - "Ce qui naît...," typescript, 1936 Sep 19 (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - "Le citoyen Vychinski," typescript carbon (2 copies), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 129)
      Includes: Spanish version, "Ee
      ciudadano Vichinsky," typescript
      carbon, corrected
    - "Comment combattent les Russes," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Nov (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - "Comment se battent les Nazis," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1942 Sep (Box 3, Folder 131)
    - "Les conditions de la victoire," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1942 Feb 17 (Box 3, Folder 132)
      Includes: table of contents page
      from Analisis, 1942 Feb-Mar
    - "Les congrès de Londres et la future internationale syndicale," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Feb 15 (Box 3, Folder 133)
    - "Conscience de l'écrivain," notes, holograph, draft, holograph, 1946 May (Box 3, Folder 134)
    - "Le coup de la fausse nouvelle," typescript, 1937 Feb 13 (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - "Crimée rouge," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - "Crimes dans l'émigration espagnole en France," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Mar 21 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - "Crimes sur crimes," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 May (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - "La crise de la civilisation européenne," outline, typescript, corrected, notes, typescript, corrected, 1941 May-Jun (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - "Crise de la victoire nazie," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - "La crise du gouvernement républicain espagnol en exil," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Feb 16 (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - "Curieux contrastes: Jakson et C-ie," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - "Défense du pilote," typescript, 1936 Oct 11 (Box 3, Folder 143)
    - [Democracy and the U. S. S. R.], typescript carbon (fragment), corrected (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - "Le dernier livre de Trotsky: "Staline," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - "Destin de la IIIe république," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Apr 7 (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - "Destin de l'occident," typescript and carbon (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - "Destin des maréchaux soviétiques...," typescript carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - "Deux défaites," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - "Les deux grandes fautes d'Hitler," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - "La deuxième phase de l'invasion de l'URSS," typescript, corrected, 1942 Jul 12-13 (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - "Discours prononcé à la réunion de deuil pour M. Wladyslaw Neuman et pour les combattants de Varsovie," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Feb 8 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - "Le Dr. Negrin et le P. C. mis en échec en France et en Mexique," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jul 31 (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - "Données sur l'Espagne," typescript and carbon (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - "Dossier de la calomnie"
      - "Le Guépéou à l'oeuvre à Mexico," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 155)
      - "Nous accusons le Guépéou," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - "Ébauche d'une plateforme socialiste," typescript carbon, 1944 Aug (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - "Économie dirigée et démocratie," typescript, corrected, 1946-47 (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - "Économie planifiée et la liberté de la presse," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Écrivains soviétiques...," typescript, 1947 Jan 14-15 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - "L'émigration espagnole au Mexique," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Feb 29 (Box 3, Folder 161)
    - "Les émigrations politiques à Mexique," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 162)
    - "L'empire nazi contre le peuple russe," bound typescript carbon, corrected, 1941 Jun-Jul (Box 3, Folder 163)
      Published in Spanish as Hitler contra Staline
    - "Les énigmes staliniennes," typescript carbon, 1944 Sep 6 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - "Es capitalista la economia nazi?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Jul (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - "L'Espagne au carrefour," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 166)
    - "L'esprit européen," typescript and carbon (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - "L'Europe de demain: néo-totalitarisme ou démocratie?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - "L'Europe en péril," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - "Existentialisme?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1946 Apr (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - "L'expansion impérialiste du Japon," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Jan 8 (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - "Expectative de la France," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1945 Feb 14 (Box 3, Folder 172)
    - "Explication d'un suicide," typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - "L'extermination des juifs de Varsovie," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 [Feb?] 28 (Box 3, Folder 174)
    - "Les faits du temps présent...," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - "La fin des trotskystes russes," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1947 Aug 29 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - "France d'aujourd'hui"
      - "La capitulation perdue," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1942 May 12 (Box 4, Folder 177)
      - "Le glissement vers la guerre-civile," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1942 May 17 (Box 4, Folder 178)
        Includes: Spanish version,
        "Deskizamiento hacia la guerra
        civil," typescript carbon,
        corrected
      - "Les origines du régime de Vichy," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), 1942 Apr 28 (Box 4, Folder 179)
      - "La plus grande trahison de l'histoire," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Apr 20 (Box 4, Folder 180)
    - "France-Espagne," typescript carbon, 1944 Oct 10 (Box 4, Folder 181)
    - [The French Revolution and the Russian Revolution], typescript carbon (2 copies), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 182)
    - "La guerre aux portes de la Transcaucasie," typescript corrected, 1942 Aug 11 (Box 4, Folder 183)
    - "Guerre de transformation sociale," notes, holograph, drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 184)
      See also: Box 21, folder 654
    - "La guerre des océans," typescript carbon, 1942 Jun 10 (Box 4, Folder 185)
    - "La guerre du Pacifique," typescript carbon, corrected, 1941 Dec 8 (Box 4, Folder 186)
    - "La guerre et la démocratie soviétique," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1941 Dec 7 (Box 4, Folder 187)
    - "La guerre et la pensée," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Aug 4 (Box 4, Folder 188)
    - "Histoire d'une fresque," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943? (Box 4, Folder 189)
    - "Histoire vraie," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1947 Nov (Box 4, Folder 190)
      Includes: Spanish version, "Relato
      veridico," typescript, corrected
    - "Un homme dans la tourmente (documents)," typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 4, Folder 191)
    - "Horizons du Caucase," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 192)
    - "Importance de la Mongolie," typescript, corrected, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 193)
    - "Indépendable," typescript (Box 4, Folder 194)
    - "Inhumanité totalitaire," typescript, 1937 Mar 13 (Box 4, Folder 195)
    - "Inquiétudes sur Largo Caballero," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jul 13 (Box 4, Folder 196)
    - "Inquiétudes sur le IIIe Reich," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Dec 24 (Box 4, Folder 197)
    - "Des interventions étrangères en Espagne," typescript, 1937 Jan 9 (Box 4, Folder 198)
    - "Jackson," typescript carbon, corrected, 1946 Jul 3 (Box 4, Folder 199)
    - "'Jackson' ou l'assassin privilégié," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Mar 21 (Box 4, Folder 200)
    - "Jakson-Mornard continue la lutte...," typescript carbon, 1943 Oct 22 (Box 4, Folder 201)
    - "La junta de liberacion de l'Espagne," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Dec 7 (Box 4, Folder 202)
    - "La 'junta suprema' du PC 'en Espagne,'" typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Apr (Box 4, Folder 203)
    - "Largo Caballero"
      - Background research material: clipping, 1945 Aug (Box 4, Folder 204)
      - Typescript carbon, 1946 spring
    - "Lenin's heir?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 May (Box 4, Folder 205)
    - "Lettres de loin"
      - "Légitime défense," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 206)
      - "Contre la calomnie," typescript, corrected, 1937 Jan 1 (Box 4, Folder 207)
        See also: Box 12, folders 410, 415
      - "D'un pouvoir fort," typescript, corrected, 1937 Jan 2 (Box 4, Folder 208)
    - "Lombardo Toledano fonde un parti...," typescript carbon, corrected, 1947 Oct 7 (Box 4, Folder 209)
    - "Ma rupture avec Trotsky," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 210)
    - [Response to José Mancisidor's article in Todo ], typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 4, Folder 211)
    - "Un manifeste pro-stalinien," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 212)
    - "Manoeuvres dans le Komintern," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Apr 10 (Box 4, Folder 213)
    - "Le maréchal hiver," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 214)
    - "La Martinique," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942? (Box 4, Folder 215)
    - "Menace sur le Caucase," typescript carbon, corrected, 1941 Oct 29 (Box 4, Folder 216)
    - "Mer blanche"
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 217)
      - Printed version, Les feuillets bleus, 1935 May 18
    - "Message à envoyer aux organisations qui ont pris l'initiative de convoquer une conférence socialiste panaméricaine--pour le 1er avril 44?," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 4, Folder 218)
    - "Mexique"
      - "Tombeau de civilisations," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Oct (Box 4, Folder 219)
      - "Cannibalisme rituel," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Nov 8 (Box 4, Folder 220)
      - "Splendeur et destruction de Tenochtitlan," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 4, Folder 221)
    - "Michoacan, Jalisco, Paracutin," typescript carbon, 1947 Jul 2-14 (Box 4, Folder 222)
    - "Misère d'Unamuno," typescript and carbon (Box 4, Folder 223)
    - "Modigliani," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 224)
    - "Mort d'Arcadi Maslov," typescript carbon, [1941?] (Box 4, Folder 225)
    - "La mort de Constantin Oumansky"
      - Background research material: clippings and press releases, 1942-45 (Box 4, Folder 226)
      - Drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1945 Jan 27 (Box 4, Folder 227)
    - "Morts en France," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Jul 29 (Box 4, Folder 228)
    - "La musée de Guadalajara," draft, typescript, corrected, 1945 Jan 16 (Box 4, Folder 229)
    - "Noëls des Russies," typescript, corrected, 1941 Oct 28 (Box 4, Folder 230)
    - "Notes d'Allemagne"
      See: Box 21, folders 656-657
    - "Nous accusons" (written with Julián Gorkin and Marceau Pivert), typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Jan 16 (Box 4, Folder 231)
      "!Acusamos!," typescript carbon
    - "Nouvelles d'Allemagne"
    - "Offensive nazie vers la Caspienne?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Oct 12 (Box 4, Folder 232)
    - "On the Russian Problem," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Oct (Box 4, Folder 233)
    - "Opinions et faits sur le question juive," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 234)
    - "Les oppositions en URSS," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1945 Jul (Box 4, Folder 235)
    - "L'organisation du Komintern," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 May (Box 4, Folder 236)
    - "Les origines du Japon moderne," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 237)
    - "Où va Staline?," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1943 Oct 4 (Box 4, Folder 238)
    - "Una página del diario de Victor Serge. Los Alemanes," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 239)
    - "Le peuple russe n'est pas totalitaire," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 240)
    - "Peuples et régimes," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 241)
    - "Planification et liberté," typescript, corrected, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 242)
    - "La Pologne et l'avenir de l'Europe," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Nov (Box 5, Folder 243)
    - "Pour Andrès Nin," printed version, Faits et documents, 1937 Jul 25 (Box 5, Folder 244)
    - "Pour l'unité internationale," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1943 Dec (Box 5, Folder 245)
    - "Premier mai des temps obscurs," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Apr 4 (Box 5, Folder 246)
    - "La presse de Mexico sur les assassins de Trotsky," typescript, corrected, 1947 Apr (Box 5, Folder 247)
    - "Le problème de la défense de Stalingrad," typescript, corrected, 1942 Jul (Box 5, Folder 248)
    - "Le problème de la liquidation de Franco," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Dec 8 (Box 5, Folder 249)
    - "Problèmes du socialisme," typescript carbon, corrected, 1945 Feb (Box 5, Folder 250)
    - "Le procès de l'assassinat de Trotsky," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Apr 7 (Box 5, Folder 251)
    - "La propagande de la C. T. A. L.," typescript carbon, 1945 Oct (Box 5, Folder 252)
    - "La puissance et débilité du Japon," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 253)
    - "Puissance et limites du marxisme," typescript carbon, corrected, and holograph, 1938 Feb (Box 5, Folder 254)
    - "Purge of Soviet Writers," draft, notes, holograph, 1946 Sep 28 (Box 5, Folder 255)
    - "Qu'attendre après l'hiver russe?," typescript, corrected, 1942 Mar 24 (Box 5, Folder 256)
    - "Que deviennent les réfugiés italiens en URSS?," typescript, corrected, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 257)
    - "Que se passe-t-il en Yougoslavie?," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Oct (Box 5, Folder 258)
    - "Quelle est maintenant la capacité de résistance de l'URSS?," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 259)
    - "La question juive," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Oct 12 (Box 5, Folder 260)
    - "Le réformisme a-t-il un avenir?," typescript and carbon, corrected, 1943 Sep (Box 5, Folder 261)
    - "Religion et révolution"
      - "La question religieuse en Russie," typescript carbon, corrected (2 copies), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 262)
      - "Vie religieuse du peuple russe," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 263)
    - [Religion in Mexico], holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 264)
    - "Réponse à des attaques du P. C.," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Jan 7 (Box 5, Folder 265)
    - "Réponse à Trotsky"
      See also: Box 21, folder 659
      - Drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1939 Aug 1 (Box 5, Folder 266)
      - Galley proofs, n.d.
    - "Réponse au questionnaire de l'ILP concernant un nouveau movement socialiste international," typescript, corrected, 1943 Dec 6 (Box 5, Folder 267)
    - "Retour à la puissance," typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 268)
    - "Russie," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 5, Folder 269)
    - "Sanglante agression communiste à Mexico," typescript carbon, corrected, [1943?] Apr 2 (Box 5, Folder 270)
    - "La servitude pénale en URSS," typescript carbon, corrected, 1946 Nov 12 (Box 5, Folder 271)
    - "Sheldon Harte," typescript carbon, corrected, 1946 Jun 10 (Box 5, Folder 272)
    - "Signification de cette guerre: guerre de transformation du monde"
      See: Box 21, folder 660
    - "Signification de Stalingrad," typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Oct 7-8 (Box 5, Folder 273)
    - "La situation en France," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Nov 16 (Box 5, Folder 274)
    - [Socialism], notes, holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected, [1942?] (Box 5, Folder 275)
    - [Socialism], drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, [1942?] (Box 5, Folder 276-278)
      Includes:
      "I. Définition du socialisme"
      "2. Le socialisme est-il scientifique?"
      "3. Matérialisme dialectique et
      dogmatisme"